A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11 FA283
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
1931-1944
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA283
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Scope and Contents note
The Commonwealth Fund established the Division of Health Studies as a separate division on April 1, 1931. The purposes of the organization were 1) to make periodic studies of the health conditions in the various communities in which the Commonwealth Fund worked, 2) assist in the development of division programs through the planning of administrative records and the appraisal of results, 3) conduct special studies in the field of health as from time to time seemed important in the development of the work of the Fund or would be of broad application.
The initial concerns of the Division were to establish the service functions of the Public Health and Rural Hospital Divisions and to aid the Mental Hygiene and Child Guidance Programs in their regular activities. The annual reports of the Division closely reflect the concurrent programs of the Commonwealth Fund. The Division's years always ended on November 1.
Dr. W. F. Walker was the first director of the Division. After Walker's death in September 1941, Dr. F. L. Moore became the new director in July 1942. Moore resigned his post on April 1, 1944. The Division of Health Studies was absorbed by the Division of Public Health on January 1, 1945.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
War relief; United States; Public welfare; Public health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; Child psychology; Child welfare; Education, Rural; Hygiene; Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Medical education; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Medicine, Rural; Harkness, Charles W.; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Columbia University; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harvard University; Social Science Research Council; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Yale University; Harkness, Edward Stephen
- Annual Report, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Report, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Report, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual Report, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Report, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual Report, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual Report, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual Report, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Budget, July 1, 1931-June 30, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Budget, September 15, 1937-December 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, January 28, 1926-December 14, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, January 11, 1929-December 31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, January 31, 1939-April 11, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, February 1, 1940-June 14, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence and Surveys of Clinics (B-H), 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence and Surveys of Clinics (Los Angeles), May 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence and Surveys of Clinics (M-S), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence and Surveys of Clinics (T), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Mental Hygiene Program Outline and Report, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Mental Hygiene Program Outline and Report, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Mental Hygiene Program Outline and Report, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)